[Music]
Heat. Hey, Heat.
Heat. Heat.
[Music]
Hello everybody and welcome to the 299th
episode of the Ask a Bijit Show. Here we
are. We are live. Let us see who all is
there on the live chat. Today we're
going to talk about history. I'm going
to answer questions that you all have
asked in the comments. I've taken a
bunch of these and I'll answer as many
as possible. Let's see who is there on
the live chat. Ara feminist player
Apurva
um Apurva Anupama Karan Ry Sumukalan
Bruce Wayne Animish Mleven Ram Nakul BM
Namaste Shivas Sai Not that guy okay sir
oritankabonia
uh Naven Sai Kushbu drawing and art
namaskar abhud Singh welcome back Sujit
Shanaga namaskarum Aayush Singh pranam
anita salutations I might take meow meow
uh geopolitical dub is here from indor
good evening sir shrias day good good
evening pratik bora nikl nikl lang kuml
krishna raunad from the surinam surin
Netherlands hello United challengers
apurwa once again sid make money with
ease
okay
is here from Assam satellite welcome
Jimmy wand matram kuml sumuk bupalam sor
pande chat DSP namast E Pranov Sony
Rea Hlay Basar Kayatwal Beyonder I
Matist Vladimir Putin
uh Ausin 439 from Agra Namaste World
affairs
uh Chatanya Manuja Artsy Weeb Pranov
Kennel Mita Sanki good evening Dur Daran
hello justep saran from Chicago hello
good morning God was alive animals for
life from laugh from Mumbai. Prashant
Sharma the seeker. Shyanga
Tiga I hope you I got your name right.
World affairs Davis Nyak Nishant Bardage
has reposted the stream on X. Good to
see you sir.
Rinki Chri good evening Deepesh Sharma
Namaste. Brianka Bonia Anahita and
IPK_1S
Prashant Sharma event countdown
Gurudatabate Sankar Coney
Chiva says Apurva Kishan Burkar Horizon
Gamer YT
Nakul BM from Karnataka thank you sir
worldly affairs Amisha Mishra hello
Junadas from Assam and so many other
people I will now stop otherwise it'll
go on forever Um, and let's take
questions. So, I'll I'll let's let's get
going with the questions. But before I
do that, let me just inform you all
tomorrow is going to be the 300th
episode. Fantastic. Outstanding. And
it's going to start at 6:00 p.m. India
time tomorrow. Okay? It's going to be an
extended extended episode. The reason
I'm telling you here right now is that
because the YouTube is making my u
community posts invisible. So I put out
a community post today early morning
India time about the 300th episode with
a link to the episode and 9 hours later
I take a look and there's not a single
comment. There's not a single like or
anything. Zero interaction. So I see
from another browser and that post is
invisible. It's not seeing it's not
visible on on my YouTube channel. So
YouTube is now making my posts
invisible. I'm not very surprised based
on what's happening on my channel since
uh election time last year, but that's
okay. So, I'm just informing you all.
Okay, tomorrow the uh 300th episode will
start at 6:00 p.m. India time. Um yeah,
just to let you know because YouTube is
playing these games now. All right,
let's get going with the questions. I
will take questions that you all have
asked in the comments.
Let us go. What questions do we have?
Question number one is by Vox Urania.
Thank you for the wonderful video.
You're welcome. Uh the question is how
have so many aspects of polytheistic
traditions managed to survive in India
which is Hinduism of course and even
thrive against uh you know the Abrahamic
Christian etc you know missionary and
all that onslaught this wisdom is needed
right so it's a great question I mean
polytheism has been eradicated the world
over more or less if you look at the
Americas Polytheism hardly survives. It
used to be the original framework in in
the Americas whether it's northern
America, southern North America, South
America, the indigenous cultures of the
native people all essentially wiped out.
Everyone has been converted. If people
practice their old culture, it's it's in
hiding mostly. Uh when it comes to
Europe, which used to practice the old
Indo-Uropean religion, entirely wiped
out. Nothing remains. Africa, it's two
foreign religions in Africa today.
They hardly practice any of their
original polytheistic faiths in Africa.
If you look at well Asia, if you look at
Arabia, Arabia, the polytheism is gone.
If you look at Persia, wiped out,
eradicated, annihilated, obliterated. If
you look at uh Greece, Rome, wherever
you go, uh even Indonesia to a large
extent and so on. So, how come Hinduism
still survives?
How does how did that happen? Despite
the subcontinent being under a under
foreign occupation for roughly a
thousand years, give or take, right? I
mean, if you look at Afghanistan now,
finally, polytheism is mostly gone.
Until the 1990s, you still had more than
100,000 polytheists in Afghanistan.
Natives natives, right? Obviously, now
it's mostly gone. uh but in the in India
it still survives. How did this happen?
What are the reasons for this? It's
important for us to know maybe this
wisdom is needed like uh Vox urania
says. So multiple reasons why Hinduism
survived. It's it's thrived also but now
it is slowly getting eradicated. Uh so
what's the deal? So Hinduism has these
characteristics diversity, plurality.
Hinduism is decentralized. It is
self-organizing.
It's got these different frameworks in
different different regions. Every
village, every town, every city has a
different framework. Every region in
India has a different framework. And
these frameworks are continuously
evolving.
These are some of the reasons why
Hinduism has survived. Polytheism has
survived in India. Another reason is the
varnati system which is demonized as the
so-called cast system. Hinduism has
survived because of the varnati system.
We've had this tremendous social
resilience, cultural resilience,
civilizational resilience because of
these things, because of the diversity,
because of the plurality, because the
Hinduism is decentralized, because it's
self-organizing, because of the varnati
system, etc. So, um,
another reason is that see Hinduism is
is not a religion that is um, you know,
a top- down religion.
you destroy the church and the and the
entire religion, you know, evaporates.
It's not like that. Hinduism is deeply
intertwined with uh every aspect. It's
historically been deeply intertwined
with every aspect of Indian social life,
daily rituals, festivals,
uh your your cultural norms, your
dietary norms,
your kinship, your traditions, your
governance, your institutions.
Historically all of that right
everything I mean everything was was
tradition and Hinduism is part of that
um deep down in the villages in in big
cities everywhere right um all the
structures in Hinduism in in the Indian
polytheism are decentralized there's no
such no no top-down structure like you
have in the Abrahamic religions in the
Abrahamic religions for example in
Christianity you have a pope at the top
then you have cardinals and you have
bishops and so on it's like it's a milit
interest organization and if you take
the top down, if you take the structure
down, everything collapses. Hinduism is
not like that, right? It's completely
decentralized. There is no single
institution.
So there's no single institution that if
you destroy it, Hinduism collapses.
Simply doesn't work. It is and Hinduism
is so diverse, so plural, super syncric.
It's absorbed all kinds of local
traditions, ways of life, you know, it's
uh it's it's given it's spawned so many
different versions of itself like
Buddhism, like Janism, like Sikhism,
right? Um tremendous philosophical
depth,
tremendous philosophical breadth also
depth as well as breadth. I mean you you
have vidanta, you have yoga, you have
the bacti movement, you have the tantric
paths. So in all of these different
aspects of Hinduism, they appeal to
various different kinds of people,
different classes of people, people with
different temperaments,
right? It Hinduism accommodates
essentially every path you can imagine,
every kind of person you can imagine,
right? Um then when um when India came
under let's say Turk occupation and
there was this this sustained attempt
over centuries to convert Indians by
force that time you had the bacti
movement right and you had various u
very prominent figures who are
considered saints like Tukaram like
Miraabai
etc who revitalized
Indian spiritual life through various
kinds of uh what they what what the um
academics would call vernacular devotion
right open to all so-called casts that
sort of thing so that's what Indian
polytheism or what you call Hinduism has
always been about it's very resilient
it's very local localized right some the
British were were they simply could not
understand Indian culture civilization
because it was so diverse. They said it
was a network of local cults everywhere
we everywhere you go and the the
so-called vernati system the so-called
cast system which actually is the
vernati vernati system they simply could
not wrap their minds around it was so
complicated so complex right um it's
it's like a federation of traditions
that sort of thing um and and you know
so the thing was that um
this vanati system they said the British
used to say that it was and and Indian
historians today will say it's it's got
these insular structures insular
community structures that uh limit
contact and and and intermarriage etc
with each other this endogami right so
because of this the verers and jatis
they became self-contained religious
units each of which would have its own
rituals its own traditions it own
lineages, its own way of doing things,
right? And it was almost impossible to
break no matter how much the oppression
was. And there were thousands, maybe
tens of thousands of varnatis.
How do you dismantle that? How do you
destroy that? Right? So these are some
of the reasons why Hinduism has endured,
Hinduism has been so resilient.
Um if you look at ancient polytheism,
polytheistic traditions like the Roman
polytheism or or the older Greek
polytheism, they did not have this
self-organizing structure, these
evolving frameworks.
They were very easy to destroy. Hinduism
on the other hand, it's the Indian
subcontinent has been inhabited since
about what 70 80,000 years before today.
It's the oldest society in the world.
And that's why it's so incredibly
complex.
And that's one of the reasons why uh
that's what why Hinduism has survived.
It's it's it's been so resilient, right?
It's very adaptive. It's very elastic,
right? It's it's the traditions are very
deeply embedded in society in in
civilization and that's why it survived.
That's why it's adapted. Um but Hinduism
is such that you know it needs state
support to thrive. It needs society to
be
to be it it needs the society to be
prosperous in order to thrive and those
things have been taken away from us
today. We don't have state support for
Indian culture Indian Indian
civilization nothing at all. The Indian
state is secular.
So today it is dying a slow death and uh
there's no funding available for for
building new temples and for continuing
the traditions. If you look at other the
other religions they have tremendous
funding and this there's their religious
structures cropping cropping cropping up
everywhere across the country. Where
when was the last time you saw a new
temple being built somewhere?
I know Ram Mandr that's one example.
What other examples do you have? So
today Hinduism is dying a slow death.
Maybe in 50 years it'll be gone.
Perhaps. I hope not. But yeah. All
right. Next question.
EE says, "Why did the USSR not construct
military bases on Indian soil if India
was a vasal of the US?" Excuse me, what?
Okay.
If so first of all you are assuming sir
that India was a vasal of the US
and then you asking why did the USSR not
construct military bases in India if the
if India was a vasal of the US
uh India was nobody's vasal okay I've
taken this question because many people
assume that maybe India was a vasal of
the USSR maybe India was a vasal of the
US maybe India was someone's vasal so
let's let's understand what the deal was
in the 20th century. India was nobody's
vasal in the 20th century. India was a
very mediocrely run country. No question
about it. Very very poor poorly run
country. Terrible governance. The way
the economy was mismanaged was terrible
and so on and so forth. I have discussed
that at great length in on this channel.
We all know that.
But what does
mean? What does it mean to be a vasal?
It means you are a subordinate
to a more powerful nation or empire or
kingdom or whatever, right? It means
subordination. Vasal means
subordination.
Now, was India a vasal of the US?
Absolutely not. I mean, who even can
imagine that? But some people would ask,
was India actually a vasal of the USSR?
So the question you have to ask yourself
was did India subordinate itself
to the USSR? Did India subordinate
India's interests to the USSR's
interests? Which means did India
sacrifice Indian interests for Soviet
interests?
I don't think that is the case. Right?
We neither sacrificed our economic
interests nor uh geopolitical interests
nor security interests nor foreign
policy interests etc
for the sake of the USSR. We had close
strategic alignment with the USSR. We
had close ideological alignment
socialism etc with the USSR. There was
strategic convergence between India and
the USSR particularly against western
influence in the subcontinent and
overall in Asia. There was no question
about the fact that there was
significant convergence between India
and the USSR. But the USSR did not
control India's
territorial integrity,
India's borders. They did not control
that. They did not control India's
economic
matters, economic uh choices, economic
strategy, tactics, whatever. The USSR
did not control India's domestic
decisions or foreign decisions. Right?
And actually India's policies
um did not always align with the USSR.
India sometimes even diverged
with um you know uh Soviet preferences
so to say for one example Christmas day
1979 what happened Christmas day 1979
the USSR invaded Afghanistan
while Gandhar India opposed that now
would a ever dare to oppose something
its master does impossible right so the
point is India was no one's wasal. India
was a mediocre country in the 20th
century. It still is to a large extent
today. Okay, let's not fool ourselves.
But we are way less mediocre today than
in the 20th century. We are actually
going in the right direction slowly
slowly incrementally glow gradually.
India is a nation of incrementalism. But
we despite all the drawbacks and all the
troubles we faced in the 20th century
all the misgovernance
all the whatever else we were still not
anyone's wasal okay so let's be very
clear about that India was not a vasal
of the US or the USSR in the 20th
century and that's why nobody was able
to construct military bases on our
territory
okay
says Hinduism often becomes the target
of the practice of child marriage. The
allegations that Hindus these these
backward Hindus they practiced child
marriage. This barbaric abominable
backward misogynistic
univilized custom of child marriage.
These terrible Hindus. So how do you
debunk this? You can't debunk it. Hindus
did practice child marriage. Evil
Hindus. But but
But since we're discussing this, let us
go to our best friend Google, right?
Satya Nadella has given us Google or he
runs Google. So let's go to our best
friend Google and let's do some
Googling. Let us do some Googling. Okay.
Um
um
at what age did Gberga
of
Burgundi
get married?
Yes. Yes.
Hey, hey, hey, hey, hey. Answer the
question. Answer the question.
Come on, you can do that.
It's not answering my question.
All right. All right. Okay. So, Gerberga
of Burgundi was a member of the elder
house of we married firstly to Herman
the first. Okay. She was born
in the year 965
and she married in the year 978 which
means that she was 12 or 13 years old
when she married. Oh my goodness that's
a child marriage. See Google is not
answering my question but I was still
still able to find the answer. This lady
okay she married the you know
at the age of 13. Now what at what age
did did Cecil of France
get married? Cecile of she was about
eight or 9 years old when she married
Tankrred prince of Galile in the year
1106.
Good god
n eight or but they will say you know
these marriages were not consummated.
Are you sure? Are you sure? Really? Is
that your your your defense now? What
year at what age did Matilda Matilda of
England the daughter of Henry I one of
my favorite kings at what age did she
get married? When she was 12 years old
and then she married again when she was
26 years old right well well child
marriage. What about Uraka of Castile?
Let's see that.
Puraka
of Castile Castile whatever they call
it. Yes. At what age did she get
married? She was married at the age of 8
to her first husband. A Christian
marriage. And the marriage was not
consummated until she was 13 or 14. My
goodness. What great mercy.
Mercy. Mercy. Oh good God. Very
merciful. U Agnes of France. Let's see.
Ag
Agnes of Thanos.
At what age did she get married? At the
age of eight. My god. The she married
the Byzantine emperor at the age of
eight. Oh my god. What what is happening
in Christianity?
What is happening here? My goodness.
Okay. What about Joan of Navar? Let us
see. Joan of
Navar.
What age did was she? She was 11 when
she got married. What about Isabella of
France?
Isabella
France.
At what age did she get married? Blah
blah etc. About 12 years old. Okay. What
about Kathine the Medici? Katherine the
Medici.
Medi,
what age was she? She was 14. My god,
that's terribly old compared to some of
the other cases we saw, right? What
about Kathine Willoughby?
Okay, let's see this one.
Katherine Willoughby. Katherine. Okay,
she was 14 years old and she married
Charles Brandon the Duke of Suffuk who
was at the time 49 years old. So a
49year-old
gentleman married a lady, a girl, a
child who was 14 years of age. What
about Lucia de Mediti?
Let us see. Lucitzia
the Medici. What age was she when she
got married? 13. She was 13. Oh my
goodness. And she died at the age of 16.
What? I wonder what she died of. Uh, I'm
sure. I'm sure it must be something um
pretty normal. What about Maria Louisa?
Maria
Louisa
of Parma. At what age did this lady get
married? At the age of 13. At the age of
13, she married Charles IV of Spain. But
I am over here giving you examples of
people who got married like hundreds and
hundreds of years ago. Obviously that's
that's very outdated information right?
No one does these things today or do
they? Let us see some other cases.
Okay. Ruby
Thornton.
Who is this Ruby Thornton?
Okay. Um Ruby Thornton. Let's just let
us just Google this name. Ruby Thornton.
Uh,
okay. 1913. How about that? Ruby
Thornton.
Okay. It's not giving me the information
I seek here.
Um,
okay. Maybe maybe we'll see somebody
else. Ununice.
Ununice
Winstead.
Marriage of Charlie Jones and Ununice
Winstead. Let's take a look at this now.
All right. Maybe this will give us
something. So, this was a child marriage
that took place in the state of
Tennessee in January 1937.
Um, how old was the girl? She was 9
years old. Oh my goodness.
Jesus Christ. She's 9 years old. Oh wow.
Okay, let's see something else. Uh, who
else do we have? Sher John Johnson.
Sher Johnson.
Sher Johnson is an American activist. Uh
she campaigned for title. Okay. She was
an only child etc etc. Beginning at the
age of nine, she was repeatedly raped by
the deacon and bishop of her church.
Well well well church bishop deacon and
she was also raped by her mother's
husband. very very very very barbaric
culture these people have. She began she
became pregnant as a result of rape at
the age of 10
and uh
okay so she had to marry the deacon who
had raped her so that he could avoid the
criminal charges.
Um okay so the church arranged the
marriage and she had six children by the
time she was 17 years old.
Okay. And this is all in the 20th
century and this lady is about 66 years
old today. Okay. I could go on and on
and on. My point is,
have we had enough?
Is Hinduism this terrible barbaric
religion?
Yeah. Yeah. Sure. There used to be the
practice of the custom of child marriage
in Hinduism. Sure.
Everyone had it. Uh let's not talk about
certain religions at all by the way, but
I've given you like a 300 examples from
Christianity.
Okay? So I'm not debunking anything. I'm
just giving you I'm just I'm just
showing you what the world really is
like. All right? That's it. Next.
Okay. Nikesh Dahal says, "What lessons
should we as ordinary Indians learn from
a millennium of humiliation?" Yes, the
Chinese speak about their century of
humiliation, don't they? They teach
every child in school about the century
of humiliation that China was humiliated
by the whites, by the westerners for a
century.
We have been under we have we were under
foreign occupation for in various parts
of the subcontinent for over a thousand
years starting with Gandhar starting
with Sind even before Gandhar and we
still are colonized by the way we still
are laboring under a colonial system
which has never been removed and we
don't know that. So our our millennium
of humiliation is continuing. By the
way, it's not over.
India remains deeply mentally,
culturally, civilizationally and
institutionally enslaved and colonized.
First of all, that is the first lesson
we have to learn. The mill the
millennium of humiliation is not over.
It is continuing. We are still
colonized. First of all, understand
that. That's the first lesson. It's not
over.
Now what are the lessons we have to
learn? Uh so many lessons. Look people
ask how do we take revenge
for the millennium of humiliation?
Revenge on the Turks, revenge on the
Europeans and so on. You don't take
revenge. The best form of revenge for
all humiliations whether in personal
life or as a civilization. What's the
best form of revenge? The best form of
revenge is success.
success. India needs to succeed.
India needs to reclaim its historical
position as the greatest civilization,
as the most prosperous civilization.
That is revenge. We are nowhere close to
achieving this revenge, right? Yeah. Uh
secondly, we have to understand, you
know, Indians love soft power. Indians
soft power. Soft power this, soft power
that blah blah blah.
Why did we fall prey to foreign
occupation?
Soft power. Maybe soft power was one of
the problems. Soft power is a mirage.
It's useless. It's worthless. Soft power
is is pointless unless it is backed up
by hard power. Actual hard power.
Understand what the world respects.
Understand what the world fears. Hard
power. Prioritize hard power.
How do you prioritize hard power? By
becoming an economic powerhouse. There's
no other way. India has to India must
reclaim its historical position as the
world's largest economy, the greatest
economy in the world. This this requires
sustained long-term high economic
growth. Right? We have to reach the $10
trillion mark first and then the $15
trillion mark. Eventually we will be uh
you know
putting out these marks in Indian rupees
not in dollars but right now we talk
about dollars because the dollar is the
world's reserve currency. So we have to
grow to these marks. Right now we are
not even a $5 trillion economy. Soon we
will be so five then 10 then 15 we have
to keep on moving. We have to keep on
heating hitting these milestones. Right?
That's the only way if you to to to
increase your hard power and gain the
respect and fear of uh those who do not
seek you well. Um and once you have
money,
you have to invest it in the right
places.
It should not be splurged on this
largely beha yojas and whatn not they're
doing. It has to be invested in the
military in science.
There's no progress without science.
Science is is is is is vital for
progress. So India needs to bolster its
military strength. India needs to
achieve excellence in science and
technology which will not come without
merit. A meritocratic society. No more
reservations.
Are we anywhere close to that? Are we
learning any of the of the lessons of
the millennium of humiliation? Right? So
we cannot compromise on excellence on
science, excellence in science and
technology. We need to have one of the
world's best space programs. Are we
anywhere close to that? Our space
program is sleeping right now. The
Chinese are going ahead in leaps and
bounds. The Chinese are developing
reusable rocket technology. What are we
doing? Nothing. Yeah. Okay. Next, India
must become a manufacturing power
obviously, right? Otherwise, you can't
grow your economy. India has to achieve
self-sufficiency in otarchy essentially
the way Russia is an utarchy completely
self-sufficient in everything whether it
is raw materials whether it is iron
whether it's copper whether it is oil
whether it's gas whether it is chemicals
whether it's fertilizers whether it is
agriculture whatever you can think of
Russia is self-sufficient in those
things so is the US India needs to
become that right completely
self-sufficient in all critical
resources agriculture industry ries etc.
technology
right complete authority
now what about leadership what about
governance
we need reforms on that we need reforms
in these fields we need to have a strong
unified leadership
the past 3,000 plus years of history
teach us that India has done well only
when it has been unified under a strong
central leadership
I can give you the examples of the
Morian Empire the Kushan Empire, the
Gush, the Gupta Empire, the Chola
Empire, even for some time, little bit
of time, the Marata Empire, strong
central leadership, right? India needs
strong central leadership to unify the
country and keep the country u immune
from external aggression.
India needs meritocracy. Like I said,
reservations are the bane of India. They
will destroy India. India also needs
meritocracy in succession of leadership.
A kingdoms,
nations, empires disintegrate
because of poor leadership succession.
And what threatens leadership
succession? Elections.
So India needs to have a system that
promotes the best possible leaders and
puts forth the best possible leaders.
Not the most popular. The best leaders
are not necessarily the most popular.
The best leaders can often be unpopular
because they make hard choices which the
general population won't understand.
Right?
So that has to happen. We need to
prioritize the national interest. We
need leaders who prioritize the national
interest. Right? Not the popular
whatever is popular right now. Yeah.
They need to avoid the the mistakes made
by past leaders. Um we have to follow
the ancient state craft of India the
Chanakeniti the timeless teachings the
precepts of Vishrishna Gupta Chanaka
right other our other rival nations they
follow Chanakini far better than us even
Pakistan follows Chanakini better than
India
so that's where we are we also need to
wage a war on corruption we need to
reform our internal systems we need to
raise our national standards heads. We
are currently a super mediocre nation.
We are a nation of incremental tiny
change.
Look at the way ISRO progresses. What
what major progress has is ISRO made in
its capabilities in the past 10 years.
2010 9 or wherever it was there we
launched Chundrean one the first one.
Where are we now? Chundrean 3. Two uh
two happened three happened. But have we
developed rockets like that are like 10
times more powerful in the past 10
years? No. Have we developed a single
reusable rocket? Have we even tested
one? No. All tiny little increments.
Lack of vision, lack of leadership, lack
of ambition. Right?
Where are we raising our standards?
We're not. Then we have to reject this
image of weakness.
this false image that has been projected
by historians and leaders that India is
is mainly historians that India is a
nation of losers and weaklings whose
core philosophy is pacifism. We need to
reject that. We need to reject that. We
have to decolonize our minds. Indians
need to mentally decolonize themselves
and we have to realize like I said that
India is still colonized and the
millennium of humiliation has not ended.
We need to reject this pacifist
ideology,
this nonviolence.
All of that needs to be dumped into the
trash bin. Don't ask yourself what would
Mr. Gandhi do. Ask yourself what would
Kali do? Yeah, that's a lesson that you
to learn from the past 10,000 years. Um,
we have to regain selfrespect in culture
and traditions. We have to regain our
sense of civiliz civil civilizational
pride. We have to learn our true
history.
Um we have to overall education. We have
to adopt Sanskrit if that's possible. We
have to be ruthless with our enemies. We
have to play the long game. I didn't
bide and so on. I mean I could give you
a two-hour lecture on this but uh I hope
you get the point of what I'm trying to
say. These are some of the lessons that
we as as a regular ordinary Indians can
learn and should learn from the past
millennium of humiliation which still
continues. We haven't come out of it. We
haven't come out of it. No matter what
your favorite leader tells you, we
haven't come out of it.
Right. Okay. Next question.
Nirvana Shanks says, "Compare the causes
of the French Revolution with the
American Revolution. what were the key
similarities and differences between
these two u major events in the western
world. So both of these uh both of these
revolutions took place in the second
half of the 18th century. The American
revolution is between 1765 and 1780
something. And the French Revolution is
in the last decade of the 18th century
about 1789 to 1799. That's the French
Revolution. So, uh these two revolutions
paired certain key points, certain key
ideals.
Uh but they arose the the the two
revolutions took place in very different
places. One is the old world, you know,
Western Europe, France. The other one is
the the new conquered world, right? The
continent that was being wiped clean of
the of the natives and it had been taken
over by the colony colonists who were
mainly English and who wanted freedom
from the crown in in London.
Uh so that's what it was. Uh so so the
two shared many things but they were
also very distinct. One thing what did
they share? What are the things that the
two revolutions shared? There was
something in Europe called the
enlightenment. Yeah. Uh so uh the
enlightenment uh it it had these these
leaders you know what of the what were
the enlightenment ideals what the French
called libeal
liberty equality fraternity uh the
sovereignty of the individual popular
sovereignty that sort of thing. So these
are these are some of the ideals of the
u European enlightenment. You had these
fantastic wonderful deep profound
thinkers like John Loach, like Jeanjac
Huso, like Mesu. uh these people they
they uh shaped the thinking of Europe
through uh their philosophy and through
their writings and they were some of the
the leading lights of the so-called
enlightenment and their ideas
deeply influenced both of these
revolutions. um both revolutions
in in both revolutions you had people
who rose up and rebelled against what
they perceived as tyranny governments
that were regarded as being as as as
unjust governments. Um the French what
did they want to do? They wanted to end
the absolute monarchy.
They wanted rule by the people. And the
American colonists they sought to break
free of the political control and of
course taxation money is very important
uh by Britain. So the British political
control and the tax that they had to pay
to the king of England they the American
colonists sought to break free of that.
So there is similarity there. Uh then
there were economic grievances right
obviously economic inequality was a very
big deal in France. exploitation of the
of the common people. So that was one of
the central problems in France and which
is why the revolution happened. Um in in
France the the poor people were heavily
taxed and u in America the the the the
colonists had to pay a 2% tax without
any representation taxation no taxation
without representation.
So the English crown, it charged a 2%
tax on the American colonists.
Today, how much income tax would the
Americans pay?
They they they they rebelled for a 2%
tax, right? Because they had to pay 2%
tax. Today, I think the income tax is in
in excess of 25%. But today, no one
rebelss.
Anyway, that's a different thing. Um so
these are some of the things that these
two revolutions had in common right. Uh
so the French Revolution it's it it took
place because of this terrible alleged
economic inequality uh this terrible
alleged social injustice that the the
system imposed on the poor people and
the absolute monarchy which was
terrible. And the American Revolution
was all about taxation without
representation and colonial independence
from Britain. They wanted to govern
their own country. They wanted to to to
have their own land. They wanted North
America to be their land. Um
and uh the French they opposed uh kings
the kings the king Louis the 15th 16th
15th whichever it was you can look it up
and the entrenched nobility aristocracy
all of that
and the American revolution it uh it
opposed the king of England. It was I
think George III, right? Uh and so on.
So the French Revolution, its goals,
what are the goals? The goals were to
radically restructure society, French
society, the complete abolition of
monarchy, the complete purging of
society of anybody who um you know was
part of the nobility of the aristocracy.
The guillotine was a great tool for
doing that off with their heads, that
sort of thing. U the French wanted
everyone to have equality under law. and
they wanted to have lacy t a secular
state and um the American revolution was
all about achieving political
independence from England and uh
self-governance
while maintaining social order obviously
you can genocide the natives that's fine
the savages like the American
Declaration of Independence says but
social order which is under the rule of
law by the white man
that sort of thing and the outcome
obviously was the was well warfare
in in France. You had this violent
upheaval in this uh decadel long
pretty chaotic transition towards
dictatorship under Napoleon essentially
right. So they moved from one form of
autocracy to another form of autocracy
in France and in America you had a
stable democratic republic that emerged
under the US constitution. Democratic
only in name obviously because the women
could not participate in the democracy
nor could the blacks nor could the nor
could the natives so democracy only for
the chosen few. Uh that's what it was.
So the American revolution was a
struggle for independence. It was a uh
struggle for governance reform and the
French revolution was a mass social
movement, mass social revolt, revolution
upheaval to to completely transform the
nature of society in France and both of
these drew inspiration from the ideas
the ideals of the European enlightenment
Montescuous John Lock and so on right
and yeah so that's kind of a comparative
analysis of the two revolutions
significant similarities but major
differences as well between these two
events.
Okay, the same questioner Nirvana Shanks
says compare the ideologies and policies
of Stalin and Mao in shaping their
respective countries.
So Joseph Stalin and Mao Tatong.
Stalin based in Moscow. Mao based in
Beijing.
Mao comes to power in 1949 after winning
the Chinese civil war and defeating um
Chankaek and the Kuin Tang and Stalin
was in power. He became well since
before the second world war.
So if you take a look at the maps then
you will see that these two countries
share a significantly long contiguous
border despite the capitals being so far
away from each other. So the Russian
capital is obviously Moscow over here
and the Chinese capital is Beijing all
the way in the east. And if you look at
the distance between the two capitals,
well it's it's mindboggling. It's 5.7
something thousand kilometers, right?
But as you can see the two countries
have a significant border. There's a
tiny little border here as well between
u
obviously Kazakhstan and Mongolia. In
the past, Kazakhstan was part of the
USSR. So, the border was much longer at
that time. So, that's just the the map.
Okay. So, yeah. Now,
so you have these two rulers, Stalin and
Mao. Both were Marxist Leninists.
Clearly, both were authoritarian.
So, the ideologies were pretty
compatible.
uh policies were also authoritarian
policies but you will find differences
as well. Um you you will find
divergences in their ideologies too and
their policies as well. So what was
Stalin's ideology? Socialism, sure. But
it was centralized industrial socialism.
H industrial socialism. And Mao, he was
also a socialist, but he was all about
revolution, the revolution of the
proletariat, the revolution of the
peasants. So Mao was all about
peasantbased socialism. Stalin was all
about industrial socialism.
significant difference despite both
being socialists.
What was Stalin's economic focus?
Stalin's economic focus was heavy
industry and collectivized agriculture.
Forcible collectivization.
You have no choice in what what happens.
We're going to forcibly collectivize all
the agriculture in the country. And
that's what he did. Stalin that's what
he implemented. So Stalin focused on
heavy industry, massive large scale
industrialization and collectivization
of agriculture. And Mao was all about
rural communes.
So Mao was all about agriculture.
It's all it was all about creating
communes in villages, rural communes. U
the great leap forward which essentially
destroyed the country in a significant
way. But yeah uh so once again Stalin
was all about industry was all about
large scale collectivized agriculture
and Mao was all about peasants once
again and rural communes not massively
collectivized agriculture and definitely
not industrialization.
Then what about the politics? What about
the political ideology? What was the
means of political control for Stalin
and Mao? So Stalin was well an out and
out bureaucratic-minded person. So
Stalin controlled his nation through a
totalitarian bureaucracy.
He held um frequent purges in the
country and he had this this massive
network of espionage all over the
country. Secret police,
NKVD, KGB, whatever you want to call it,
right? So the bureaucracy controlled the
whole country totalitarian bureaucracy
and you had secret service all over the
place and uh yeah purges happened all
the time in Stalin's USSR.
When it comes to Mao Mao uh how did he
control his country? through mass
mobilization of the peasants
through ideological campaigns that
sought to motivate the peasants
and uh yeah you would obviously have
aeroplaning of of intellectuals and all
that you can look it up what it what
what it means black and white pictures
thankfully right uh and that was called
the cultural revolution so the total
transformation of the culture of the
country
uh what was the role of the peasants in
the two countries. Under Stalin, the
peasants were forcibly
subordinated to the industrial goals of
the country. So peasants were sometimes
moved out of agriculture and put to work
in in factories, right? And in Mao was
China, it was the other way around.
People who worked in factories were
pushed into farms and and turned into
peasants. And the peasants were
essentially Mao's centralized
revolutionary force.
So totally different outlook in the two
countries. Um and obviously both Mao and
Stalin were against religion. So Stalin
definitely suppressed religion in his
country. Anyone was who was religious
would be purged. And Mao was not only
about opposing religion and purging
people who were religious. Mao was also
an anti-intellectual.
So there was this massive
anti-intellectualiz
anti-intellectualism
campaign in China.
If you were a physics professor and you
taught quantum mechanics, you would be
purged. You would be sent you would be
sentenced to 20 years hard labor in the
farms and you will forget all quantum
mechanics by the time you're done.
Right? Mass reeducation. Anyone who had
the wrong notions,
you believed in quantum mechanics, you
believed in relativity, you would be
re-educated.
Yeah. Through through hard labor, that
sort of thing.
So, as you can see, the ideologies are
similar but very different. The policies
are also kind of similar, but
tremendously different as well. And uh
and Mao to conclude, Mao regarded
Stalin. Mao had the greatest amount of
respect and admiration for Stalin and
it's only after Stalin's death that the
Sino Soviet split happens because once
Kruev comes in Mao did not have that
same kind of respect for GeF
both were similar but both were also
significantly different.
Amisha says, "Ancient Egyptians were
fairly accepting of nudity with women
often depicted depicted topless or in
little clothing. But today millions of
Egyptian women wear conservative Islamic
clothing. How did they become more
conservative?
Did it happen in the Greek period? Did
it happen at some in some other period?
Was it the Roman period? Was it the
Christian period, the Muslim period? How
did this all evolve?" Uh so you are
totally right. uh if you look at uh
various uh carvings and sculptures and
you know artwork Egyptian artwork you
you will see that the Egyptians were
were you know nudity was no big deal in
Egypt whether it was males or females no
big deal at all so how does this change
so that is the original Egyptian culture
very similar to ancient Indian culture
before 1000 AD no big deal unity is no
big deal u so Egypt
It first came under foreign occupation.
Egypt is a very ancient civilization.
Egypt was well, you could say older than
China. The only older civilization is
India that we know of. So, uh
Egypt first came under foreign
occupation about 1500 BC. Uh for a
century and a half, maybe two centuries
by a strange num bunch of people called
the Hixos.
The Hixos were very different from the
Egyptians. They were of of course
polytheists and they used to worship a
thunder god.
They used to
invade on chariots
and yeah certain very strange beliefs
they had. They had horses and they had
chariots and they had a thunder go
thunder god and they had copper weapons
and stuff like that and they seems they
seem to have come from the from the part
of the world where the mitani lived and
so on. Um but the Hixos did not impose
any weird culture on on on Egypt that uh
made Egypt cover up or something like
that. That did not happen. So the Hixos
occupation did not
change Egyptian culture in a way that
you know nudity became unacceptable.
Then in the 4th century BC
uh around that time Egypt was under
Persian occupation and the Egyptians
regarded the Persians as as bad people.
Okay, foreign occupiers of of of Egypt.
And the Persians again had no issue with
nudity, nothing. The Persians were
similar to us at the time. So they they
they had no issue with nudity. But then
the Greeks arrive. Alexander the Greek
comes there. He had already defeated the
Persian forces in what is present day
Syria. And then before going to Persia,
he said let me go towards south towards
Egypt. So he uh moves into Egypt and the
Egyptians welcome him as a liberator and
they they crown him as the pharaoh
Alexander. And he Alexander apparently
founds a new city which is now called
Alcandria Alexandria
uh based on his name. Yeah. And the
Greeks also don't have any issue with uh
nudity at the time. So that's the 4th
century BC.
Now around the first century AD things
start changing because a strange new
religion appears is it's introduced into
Egypt. It's called Christianity. Right?
somewhere in the first century AD. At
that time, uh it's not Greece that's
ruling ruling Egypt, it's Rome now
because Greece was occup conquered and
occupied by the Romans and then Julius
Caesar happens and Mark Anthony happens
and Cleopatra happens and Egypt becomes
a Roman possession. So in the first
century AD, you see this new thing
spreading through Rome and it also
reaches Egypt. So Christianity arrives
in Egypt in the first century AD. Um and
eventually Rome officially becomes
Christian somewhere in the 4th century
AD and this is what is imposed on Egypt
as well. Um you you have the the the
female astronomer and mathematician
Hitesia who was torn to pieces by
Christian mobs uh somewhere in the in
the 4th century AD. Right? So because
she was a mathematician, she was a
woman. How dare a woman be do
mathematics? Right? That sort of thing.
Um
and Christianity was significantly
more intolerant than the Greek
polytheistic religion or the Roman Roman
poly polytheistic polytheistic religion
or obviously the original Egyptian
polytheistic religion. Christianity did
not like women who were free. It did not
like nudity. So things start changing
when Christianity becomes more powerful
in Egypt. And somewhere in the sixth
century or so AD uh Egypt's ancient
culture is wiped out and that's where
Christianity becomes more orthodox and
so on and becomes more powerful and I
think it's it's around this time that
you know nudity is no longer tolerated
in uh Egypt
and then
um there is a conquest of Egypt
somewhere in the 7th century or or so by
the Arabs
and that that's about
We know what happens then. The uh
Rashidun caliphate. So once the Rashidun
Caliphate conquers Egypt, its curtains
for any
idea of nudity or whatever you have to
cover up top to bottom. End of story.
All right.
Aayush Singh says, "You mentioned that
Indians settled in Australia thousands
of years ago. It means that they had the
chance to conquer the piece of
territory.
Why didn't they do this like the
Europeans? Why such a difference in
mindset
where one race conducts genocide on a
continental scale like in North America,
South America etc. Whereas the other one
which had reached regions which
Europeans did not even dream to have
existed at least the time lived in
harmony. Also please give an estimate
number of people Europeans have killed
in Australia, Americas and countries
like New Zealand. Okay.
So there is no question about the fact
that ancient Indians voyaged to
Australia. When did this happen?
Somewhere around 4,300 years ago. You
can look it up. You will find articles
in Nature. You will find National
Geographic articles and so on. The time
period is about roughly 4,300 years
before today. Give or take a 100 or 200
years around that sort of time period.
How do we know this happened?
How do we know? Because that's the time
when new genetic seniority appear among
the native population of Australia. Who
the the who are the natives of Australia
today? They are called the Australian
Australian Aborigines.
the Aboriginal people of Australia.
They're not called the indigenous
Australians. I suppose they may be
called that, you know, but the the term
that I have heard since I was a kid was
Australian aboriges.
So that's the native true native people
of Australia, not the Europeans. So
these people have been living in
Australia for at least 50,000 years.
50,000.
And suddenly about 4,300 years ago,
their genetics change and some new genes
come in a set of new genetics appear in
the Australian populations and these
genetics are clearly
Indian subcontinental genetics. So if
you look at Australia's population
today, the native population of
Australia today, approximately 10
between 9 to 11% of their genetics on
average are of Indian origin and you
will find more Indian origin genetics in
the north and west of Australia. Let's
take a look at the map, shall we? So
that we understand what we are talking
about.
All right, here is map.
So you can see where India is now. You
can see where Australia is. What is the
north of Australia? It's all of this,
right? What is the northwest of
Australia? It's this clearly it's the
region of part of Australia that is
closest to India.
So Indians voyaged by sea maybe through
Southeast Asia or or wherever, but it
they voyaged by sea. Indians had ships.
Indians could undertake sea voyages and
they they appeared in Australia. We
don't know whether Indians settled there
or Indians stayed there for a while or
Indians visited there regularly but
Indian genetics appears there which
means that Indians interbred
with the people of Australia
and if you look at the northeast of
Australia that's where you will have
more Indian genetics than maybe southern
Australia Tasmania whenever Tasmanians
are obviously have been completely
genocided out of existence by the whites
but um in other parts of Australia
natives still exist. So more Indian
genetics in the northwest of Australia
and central Australia compared to
southern Australia. Um and this all
appears about 4,300 years before today.
What also changed in Australia around
that time exactly at that time is that a
new species of animal appeared in
Australia. Exactly when these new
genetics arrive Australia. In Australia
what new species of animal arrived? Let
me show you.
It's called Australian lingo which is a
nice dog. This if you look at this dog
this is your standard issue Indian dog
that you will see on every see on every
street corner. It's the same dog. So
this dog suddenly appears in Australia
which was not in available in Australia
ever before and this dog looks like your
standard Indian street dog right. Um so
yeah so a new dog a new animal appears
in Australia. Clearly the Indians
brought this dog as well and new tools
also appear in Australia around this
time and even new a new language family
appears in Australia around this time.
Um so that is what we know clearly
Indians went there. Um
was it a single voyage? Were there
multiple voyages? Did Indians stay there
and have local wives or whatever and
then leave? We don't know what happened,
who the people were, who the ancient
Indians were. At the same time, we have
the Yamna invasion of Europe that's
happening. At the same time, we have the
introduction at the same time of Indian
cattle in West Asia in Egypt. So,
Indians seem to have been traveling
across the world at this time and they
reached Australia and they did not do
any genocide of the Australians.
Clearly, there is zero evidence of that.
So Indians,
they
they interacted pretty peacefully with
the Australians. That's what we know,
right? And why did Indians not do what
the whites did to Australia? It's a it's
a cultural thing. It's a cultural thing.
It's a civilizational thing.
Um yeah. Do we have an estimate of how
many native Australians were killed by
the Europeans? Um, I'm not sure about
the in in Australia proper how many were
wiped out. Okay. Uh, Abori. Abori.
Okay. Enslaved. My goodness. What's
wrong with me? E N S L A V
E D. Ah man. So if you look at the
images you will see that Austral the
Australian Aboriginal people were
treated like animals.
Uh they were treated like flora and
fauna. I mean check this out. People in
in chains.
Uh it was it was absolutely terrible
atrocious uh treatment that these people
got. They were treated like animals and
many of them would have been killed. Uh,
another question we can ask Google is
how many
native
Tasmanians
existed before Euro Europeans
uh appeared. Let's see.
Oh, really? Just 15,000 people in
Tasmania. Okay, that's what Google says.
All right. So between 3 to 5 15,000
people only were genocided in Tasmania.
What about the Americas? In North
America maybe 100 100 million between 50
to 100 million uh native Americans were
genocided in North America. In South
America I I'm not not quite sure. You
can look it up. So yeah, New Zealand
once again I'm not really sure and we
can do the do the research alo over here
or you can do it in your free time but
the numbers are pretty pretty
mindboggling overall.
Right. David says how did the Saxon
Empire beat the Roman Empire?
Okay, we're talking about uh the British
islands, aren't we? So let's take a look
at the map before we go and discuss this
further.
Um the Saxon Empire and the Roman
Empire. Okay. So here's a map of the
world. We're talking about the British
islands. So this is the part of the
world. We're talking about this two sets
of set of islands over here. So Rome is
over here in Italy. As you can see, this
is Rome. This is the city of Rome. And
if you go to the north and you go to the
west, you cross the English Channel, you
come to the British islands.
And um
so so the the Romans conquered the
British islands, not all of the British
islands. They could not conquer Ireland.
They did not really go all the way into
Scotland, but what is now called England
and Wales and Northern England, all of
that was conquered by the Romans. And
they they built a wall. Hadrien's wall
all the way up north and north of the
wall were the barbarians, the picss and
whatnot.
And eventually the Romans left England.
So what happened is the question. Did uh
the Saxons defeat Rome? Did the Saxons
have an empire? The Saxons never had an
empire and they never defeated Rome. So
what happened? How come England became
Anglo-Saxon?
How come the British islands were
dominated came to be dominated by the
Anglo-Saxon people
and today and later the Normans. So when
the Romans arrived in the British
islands, it starts around the time of
Julius Caesar. The people who lived in
the British islands, they were of Celtic
origin mostly.
Um
and they were defeated by the Romans and
the Romans you know built garrisons and
cities in the British islands and uh
they they conquered and ruled the
British islands. Now in the 4th century
AD
uh that's like several centuries have
passed and Rome is no longer this great
cohesive power that it used to be. It's
been an empire for like two three
centuries and once you're an old empire
you you kind of lost lose your edge
don't you? Uh you overextend yourself.
You have too many possessions too many
things to look after. You have gmania
you have th you have North Africa you
have Egypt you have Greece
you have Gaul you have uh Iberia you
also have the British islands. How much
can you can you can you administer and
govern at the same time?
So by the by the fourth by the fifth
century AD what you find is that Rome is
politically fragmented. Rome is under
pressure by invaders. Um a bunch of
Germanic tribes have come together you
know into a coalition and they have
crossed the rine. Where's the rine? Let
me show you the Ryan since we are
discussing the Ryan. The Ryan is a major
Euro river in Europe.
Uh let's go. So the way I see the Ryan
is the border between Switzerland and
Germany. Okay, if you go to the map, you
will find that there is this river over
here.
This is the Ryan. Right in the middle of
the Ryan, you have the border between
Switzerland and Germany. And Switzerland
was then at that time part of Gaul.
The Romans regarded the uh this yeah
this land as part of Gaul.
So the Germanic tribes had crossed the
Rine and they were threatening Gaul and
they did devastate Gaul. And then you
also had the Ostrogoths and the
Visigoths who were doing all kinds of
mischief and
devastation of Rome. You also had the
Vandals.
You also had the Hoons. The Huns who
were pressuring Rome at the same time
when they were pressuring India. So Rome
is under siege from all these forces.
Rome is overextended.
Rome is also politically disunited. Rome
has ambitious governors who want to
declare independence and declare
themselves emperor. Right? Uh it
happened a couple of times. Once in the
late 4th century, once in the early
fifth century. What what year was it?
406 407 AD. Constantine the third or
something his name was was a Roman
governor who declared himself emperor
and fought the empire itself. That sort
of thing happens.
U so you have all these issues with
Rome. Um and by about 410 AD,
so when somebody rebelss against Rome,
your own governor, you have to bring in
re reinforcements to defeat him. And if
this happens in western France, which is
today, today's Western France, which was
then western Gaul, then some then you
may have to bring in re reinforcements
from the armies that are stationed in
England. So if you take this ar armies
out of the British islands to fight the
rebels in France then Britain becomes
undermanned
and the local tribes will try and fight
the Romans. So eventually a situation
occurred by about 410 or so AD
that the that the emperor of Rome sent a
message to the cities in Britain which
are ruled by Roman governors that no
more help is coming from Rome. you are
on your own. So those Roman governors
etc. they declared independence. They
became kings or chieftains in their own
right and then Rome comes under
comes under a new invasion. The Saxons,
the Angles and the Saxons. They invade
England. So Rome withdrew voluntarily.
It was never defeated by the Saxons.
Okay. Rome had too many problems. It
eventually had to abandon England. But
many Roman origin people remained in
England and they became English overall
eventually. And then you had the Saxon
invasion and then allegedly there was a
king called Arthur who defeated the
Saxons and the invasion was reversed for
a few years and there is archaeological
evidence of that as well that the
invasion was reversed for a while but
eventually the Saxons and the Angles
they settle in England and this they set
up the Anglo-Saxon uh era of England
which lasts for a few centuries until it
is
replaced you know. So the Saxons,
Anglo-Saxons ruled England for close to
half a millennium
before and and then the Normans took
over. They defeated the Anglo-Saxons.
The last Saxon king was Harold.
Yeah. Harold Goodwinson, the
unfortunate, the guy who took an arrow
in his eye. And that's a whole different
story. Okay. So that's the story about
the Romans and the Saxons.
Real painter. That's quite a name.
Okay. Why did the US invade Vietnam? Was
Vietnam became becoming a USSR
with the communism split? Okay. What was
the deal? What happened?
So in 1945 the US in 1944 455 the US
becomes u a superpower you know the
world's reserve currency and so on and
it it wins second the second world war
along with Russia and Europe is divided
between eastern and western Europe.
Western Europe comes under US hedgemony.
Eastern Europe comes under Soviet
hedgemony.
Um at that time Vietnam was under French
occupation,
French colonization.
The the the term we use is colonization
because occupation sounds harsh.
Colonization is a nice term. So Vietnam
was under French colonization.
Occupation. Okay.
And there was this uh this gentleman
called Ho Chi Min who was French
educated
who was a communist who wanted to make
Vietnam independent of the French. So
there was a communist rebellion going on
in Vietnam in the 1940s 1950s. By 1954
the French are defeated
and the northern part of Vietnam is
liberated from the French. So the
Americans hop in and they prop up a pro-
west government in South Vietnam.
I can't remember the name of the guy who
was ruling South Vietnam at the time,
but there was a pro- US government.
Have you seen that infamous picture of
the Vietnamese Buddhist monk?
What was the deal? Okay, so
Vietnam
Buddhist
monk self emulation
okay very okay very um famous infamous
image trigger warning in case you are
sensitive don't look at this
this here
how do I
okay maybe it doesn't want to allow me
to see this
or show you this.
But you have this picture, right? Very
famous, infamous picture of the Buddhist
monk who who emulates himself. The why
did he do this? Why did Tich Kuang Duk
do that? Why did he set himself on fire?
This was in South Vietnam.
Why did he do this? Because the South
Vietnam government that was propped up
by the US was a Christian government and
it was trying to eradicate the native
religion and culture of Vietnam.
Naturally, obviously if you are a pro-
US government, you're going to do that.
So that's why this Vietnamese Buddhist
monk did this public self- emulation.
So coming back to the question, South
Vietnam was a US vasal. It was propped
up by the US. So you have successive
American governments and presidents uh
Truman, Eisenhower,
uh Kennedy etc. who support South
Vietnam more and more first through
funds, then through political advisers,
then through military advisers, then
through weapons and so on. And there's
the you know the the quantum of
involvement is is increasing every year
with each presidency
with each administration with each
American regime. And uh the American
fear was that look in 1949 China became
communist
and now North Vietnam has become
communist. If we allow this to happen
there's going to be a domino effect and
the whole of Asia will become communist
and we want democracy. Communism is
something that came out which which is
which is associated with the USSR. So if
communism spreads the USSR wins and we
lose. So let's have democracy which is
vasalage.
Understand what democracy really means?
It means being a vasal of the US. Um so
so so North Vietnam becomes more and
more powerful and they are obviously
supported by the USSR as well as by
China. So the US
obviously supports South Vietnam and
eventually by 1964 there is this alleged
false false flag operation. Okay, some
people say it's a false flag operation.
Others say it's a conspiracy theory.
It's up to you to decide what you feel
or what you think based on your research
if you do if you do it. So there is this
Gulf of Tonkin incident. Let's Google
it. H
Gulf of Tonkin
incident.
So
it's a it's a couple of American
warships that allege that they were
attacked by North Vietnamese vessels and
that gives the US the justification for
launching a war on on North Vietnam. And
that's the beginning of the Vietnam war.
Eventually they bombard Cambodia as well
and the war spills over and so on and
eventually the US is defeated and the
whole of Vietnam is reunified under the
North Vietnamese government. Ho Chi Min
and Saigon becomes Ho Chi Min city and
today Vietnam is well still well the if
if you see the flag of Vietnam it's
still that communist flag. So that's the
story of why the US invaded Vietnam.
Right. Next,
Amisha says, "If the Ottomans were
Turks, then how come they all look like
Europeans today?
Was the Ottoman Empire considered
European by other European nations and
peoples?" Absolutely not. The Ottoman
Empire was not considered European by
anybody, including the Ottomans
themselves.
The Europeans did not regard the Ottoman
Turks as Europeans. They regarded them
as Turks. Turks aren't Europeans. So the
Ottomans were indeed Turks. Uh we don't
know that. We don't know whether Erru
even existed. But the later Turks
obviously did. Otman and his
descendants.
And they did not look like Europeans at
all. They looked like central Asian
Turks, people from uh Kazakhstan or or
or or Turkmanistan or whatever, you
know, that sort of appearance.
So, how did the modern Turks end up
looking the way they do they look today?
They don't look like central relations.
They look like Europeans. What happened?
See the Turks when they um invaded
Anatolia and what is now Turkey which
used to be Greece at the time when they
invaded they had already converted to
Islam the Turks
um and they still retained this ancient
Turic custom
of bride kidnapping.
Bride kidnapping is how you prove if you
are a Turkic warrior and you want to
transition to adulthood to manhood. If
you want to prove that you are worthy of
being a warrior and worthy of being a
man, you have to take a great risk. You
have to go and raid a neighboring tribe
or some other tribe and kidnap a girl, a
young girl and bring her back. If you
survive and if you're able to bring the
girl back, you get to marry her. you get
a wife and you are then respected as a
man. Yeah, you could do it. Good. Good
on you, bro. That sort of thing. So that
was this Turk tradition,
pre-Islamic tradition.
And uh so now the Turks invade Anatolia.
They conquer Anatolia. They find this
land which is pretty fertile, nice
temperate climate. It doesn't freeze in
the winters.
Yeah. big population, completely
peaceful, helpless population, lots of
women. So what do the Turks do? They go
and grab girls
and forcibly marry them.
And because they are now Muslims, one
woman isn't enough for them. So they
grab multiple women, each Turk.
And this goes on for generations and
generations and generations. If you go
to Cyprus today,
where is Cypress?
in in the 1970s, which year was it? 1974
or whichever year it was, sometime in
the 1970s, the Turks invaded the Greek
island of Cypress. Where is Cyprus? This
here is Cypress. It is a Greek island
and the Turks take over the northern
part of Cypress. As you can see, there
is this dash line over here which which
is which represents an undemarcated
disputed border and a no man's land kind
of situation here. Yeah.
So the northern Cypress is occupied by
Turks. Southern Cypress is occup is is
still free and it is still Greek. So in
Cyprus also ever since the Turks took
over, they have been trying to kidnap
Greek women and girls and forcibly marry
them and have children with them. So
that still continues. So because the
Turks continued this for generations and
centuries, that's why the Turks today
look like Europeans.
And if you do a DNA test of Turks of the
Turkish people, you'll find that there
are about 95% to 100% either Greek or
Greek Armenian or something similar.
Very little if any central Asian DNA
left today. Maybe 1 2% because they've
been doing this for centuries.
So that's how they completely
transformed their their ethnicity
and so they are culturally Turkish or
Turkish today but ethnically they are
Greek and Armenian but they hate the
Greeks and Armenians
that's the deal
okay
uh two questions one is by EE how did
capitalism evolve from feudalism and
Nirvana Shanks says how exactly did the
industrial field revolution change
social hierarchies and labor systems in
Britain. Thank you for your attention to
this matter.
Okay.
So clearly the two questions are
interconnected and uh let's deal with
this. Okay. So the industrial revolution
is it happens sometime in the 18th
century. Let's say 18th century. Okay.
Industrial revolution.
before the industrial revolution
happened, what kind of society did you
have in Europe? What kind of society did
you have in England? Because it it it
mainly comes from England, you could say
the industrial revolution.
What was the nature of English society
before the 18th century? How was English
society in the year 1066 AD when William
the Conqueror takes over England? How
was English society in the 1200s, 1300s?
How was it? It was a feudal society.
What do we mean by a feudal society? It
was an agricultural society where you
had a very strongly entrenched cast
system, a highly oppressive and
hierarchal cast system. At the very top,
you have the royalty,
the royal family and their relatives.
That's at the very top. At the top of
that you have the crown.
Then you have the knights,
the chosen warriors of the king or the
queen. Mainly the king. Okay. The
knights. Below the knights you have the
aristocracy and nobility which is strong
men or thugs who have been given various
land holdings by the king to administer
on the king's behalf. So every year
these thugs who are called nobles they
will give a tax to the king. They are
his vasals. That's where the word vasal
comes from. Okay. The French called them
the vasals and the English called them
nobles and so on.
So that was where the power lay. And
these these nobles they would have their
own soldiers and whenever the king
needed the soldiers they would go and
fight for the king.
So that's about maybe 5% of the
population,
the royalty, the knights, the the the
the the nobility and their soldiers.
That's about 5% of the of the
population. About 95% of the population
were peasants,
people who worked as farmers, people who
worked in various professions.
And they were horribly oppressed.
And most people in England worked on
farms, worked in rural areas.
And the wealth of the country of the
kingdom lay in agricultural produce.
And what gave you agricultural produce?
Land. Farmland. So farmland was
incredibly valuable. And it was
controlled by these nobles who served
the king. And the peasants who worked in
the farms, they did not own anything, no
land, nothing. They simply were allowed
to work on the land and they had to give
most of the produce to them to the
nobles and just barely subsisted. That
was the deal. A highly unequal society,
tremendous
uh power differential, tremendous
inequality and a deeply en entrenched
cast system.
That's what you had. That was feudalism
in England.
So what was so what was the source of
the wealth of the nobility and the kings
and all that? The land, the agricultural
land. Okay. Now the industrial
revolution happens and society changes.
How does it change? Now
the the the wealth it now starts coming
from industry.
industry. These machines,
they produce goods that are very
valuable, far more valuable than
agricultural produce.
And these industries, they are based in
these new mushrooming towns and cities,
Manchester and whatever else.
So suddenly you have this these business
people, these entrepreneurs
who very rapidly become more wealthy,
significantly wealthier than the the
oldtime nobles. And these peasants who
used to toil away on the farms, they now
gravitate towards the big cities because
there is money to be made in the big
cities. But once again in the big cities
you they they find that they they own
nothing. They own no land. They don't
they don't own any property. They live
in rented houses in crowded squalid
rented houses and they sickly start
mushrooming and becoming big and you
have overcrowding, you have pollution,
you have horrible hygiene, you have
epidemics, you have disease
and once again you have tremendous
inequality
and it's the business people who become
wealthy, super super wealthy and the
nobles they retain some prestige, they
retain some land but they are no longer
wealthy. And so you have a tremendous
transformation of society.
The society transforms from a feudal
system to a capitalistic system. That's
how capitalism evolved from feudalism
and it created this whole new set of
hierarchies. It destroyed the old cast
system to some extent. The naves still
continue and it created these new labor
systems. Right? So you have the rise of
the bourgeoisi
which is the entrepreneurs the ones who
own the means of production and you have
the rise of the proletariat which is the
peasants who used to work on the farms
and then they now work in these terribly
horrible factories. So you have this
whole new system that emerges out of the
ruins of feudalism because of the
industrial revolution, right?
Rahul Dunke says, "How did Christopher
Columbus
make such a blunder reaching America
thinking it to be India when the
direction
is totally opposite? How could he march
towards the west thinking it's the east?
Wasn't he reading the magnetic compass,
the position of sun in the night? Wasn't
all of this informative enough?
So, Christopher Columbus, he did have
the use of the magnetic compass, but it
was a new instrument at the time. So, it
was there. It was available to him. Now,
what was the deal with Christopher
Columbus?
He knew India existed. See at this time
in the 1500s what's recently happened is
that the Turks had recently conquered
Constantinople and they had finally
ended the Byzantine Empire the western
the eastern Roman Empire and because of
that Europe had lost its its its land
access to India. Europe used to trade
with India for centuries for since
before the Roman times and they deeply
craved Indian goods such as uh textiles
such as spices and and whatever else.
So um the European kingdoms and empires
they desperately sought to find a
different way to access India a
different route through some other part
of the world. uh they could no longer go
by land. So maybe they wanted to find
some way of reaching India by the sea.
Now around this time around the 1500s
they people had realized that the world
is round. So Columbus said you know we
keep trying going east but if the world
is round what if I just go westwards I
I'll go west I I I'll reach India from
the other side. Um so his reasoning was
sound and his motivation was pure greed.
He had promised his patrons the queen
and king of Spain that he would go and
discover India and bring back tremendous
amounts of gold from India. Well that is
weird because the Europeans typically
sent gold to India in exchange for the
spices and and whatever other goods they
used to buy. But whatever.
So the king and queen of Spain were
super greedy and Columbus was personally
ambitious and personally super greedy
and he promised them that he would get
back so much gold and what not. He would
discover India was was sure of it. So
they financed his expedition the Santa
Maria and all these ships like two three
ships they gave him or he he acquired
for with the wealth with the money they
gave him and he goes westwards right
across the Atlantic and he is lost over
there and eventually he does discover
he's his crew discovers
land but he claims that he discovered it
himself obviously right and uh they he
obviously had reached to the Caribbean
islands and he claimed it was India and
he proceeded to enslave the people of
Hispanola. Would you like to see the
map? I'll show you the map. Um, where is
Hispanola? Right, that's the question
you would be probably wondering about.
So, where is map? Here's map. We go
westwards. So, it starts he starts off
from Spain. He stops at the Canary
Islands over here to to uh replenish his
ships and then he goes
westwards and he reaches somewhere here
and eventually he colonizes this island
and genocides the people there. This
island was then called Hispanola. Today
it is divided into two countries
Dominica and Hiti.
And he also discovered Cuba and so on.
He did at least three voyages. He
eventually got lost during the third
voyage and he discovered Venezuela. So
when he discovered the Dominican
Republic and Cuba and all, he thought
that one of these was Japan and the
other was India.
And he goes back to Spain and reports
that you know what I have discovered
India. So uh he was convinced that he
had discovered India. I don't blame him
for that. At the time nobody knew where
they were, right? And the compass
doesn't tell you what country it is.
And Columbus clearly was not at all
familiar with what India was like, what
India's cultures culture was like,
customs were like,
geography was like. So he found
something and he said that it was India.
And that's what happened.
Okay. Shou says, "What faith or religion
did the Nazis believe in?"
Um, Jesus Christ, Christianity. That's
what the Nazis believe in. Believed in
that was their religion.
Christian Christianity.
Pretty simple answer this time.
Okay. Next question. Nirvana Shanks
says, "Sparta was military dominant but
socially rigid. How did its strengths
also create vulnerabilities?"
Okay. So, first of all, where is Sparta?
We have all heard of Sparta. Let's go to
the map and discover Sparta, shall we?
Let us go to the map and discover
Sparta. So, we are here in India. We go
westwards, westwards, westwards. We
reach the Mediterranean
and then we move further west of Cit
and here we shall find Sparta. So, let's
just search for it. Sparti
and zoom in. Here we are. So this is the
old, you know, the earthw wild Sparta.
What's it look like? Well,
so that's where Sparta is.
And uh as you can see,
how far is it from Athens? Let us see
measure distance. It's about 150
something kilometers from Athens as the
crow flies. So that's where Sparta lies
in present day Greece.
Okay. Now let's talk about Sparta.
We're talking about classical Greece u
which is about what 600 500 BC around
that time 400 even 400 BC
that's classical Greece. So, uh, Sparta
obviously was renowned for its
militaristic culture.
Um, very rigid, very harsh militaristic
c culture, extremely high standards. And
the Spartans fought the Athenians. They
fought Athens in the Peloponyian war and
they defeated Athens. That war lasted
decades and they eventually defeated
Athens. That led to the downfall of
Athens. Eventually, Sparta itself fell.
eventually to the Romans. Now, what's
the deal with Sparta? It was militarily
dominant. It was able to defeat Athens.
So, clearly, it had tremendous
advantages.
Socially rigid. Okay. So, what's the
deal with Sparta?
So, as you saw, Sparta was located on
this massive peninsula which was
connected by this land bridge, you could
say, to the region where Athens exists,
right? What was Spartan society like?
Right? That's the question we have to
ask ourselves. How many Spartans were
there?
Spartan society was very strange.
They were all soldiers. Their only
profession was warfare.
But how can a society only practice
warfare? Who's going to plow the fields?
Where's the food going to come from?
Who's going to take care of the
industries or whatever else? Who's going
to build houses? If you are only
soldiers, if your profession is only war
fighting and sword fighting, who does
all of that? Where does the food come
from? Who does the fishing? Who does the
farming? Who does the animal
agriculture, animal husbandry?
Where will you get the carpenters from?
Where will you get uh you know people
who make clothes? Where does all that
come from is the question, right?
Well, you know, the fantastic thing is
that Sparta's the majority of Sparta's
population was slaves.
So, if you had one warrior,
you had seven slaves for that one
warrior.
H what were these slaves called? They
were called helots. H E L O T. Helot,
plural is helot. So the helotss were the
people the majority people of Sparta.
Maybe they were an ethnicity, maybe they
were a tribe, maybe they came from a
place called Helos, we don't quite sure,
but they were called the Helotss. And
they were enslaved
by the warrior cast of Sparta.
And you know what was the manner of
enslavement?
Every helot was allocated
a certain number of beatings per year.
There was a kota given to every helot
that you have to be beaten x number of
times per year and it would all be you
know the records will be kept and if you
were not beaten let's say the the the
kota was 20. So if the year is ending
and like seven days are left and he has
been beaten only only 10 times then over
the next seven days he would be beaten
10 10 more times. That's the kind of
thing you had. And they would be
humiliated by making them wear caps made
of dog skin and whatnot. And their
women, I have no idea what happened to
the women and children, but yeah, it was
a it was a it was a tremendously
oppressive society. If you watch movies
like 300, they portray the Spartans as
this great heroic people. They were
brutal oppressors.
They enslaved their own people
essentially.
Hm. The Spartans, none of this will be
taught to you in in your history
textbooks or or by Hollywood movies,
right?
So for for every warrior you had seven
slaves minimum, men, women, children,
what kind of society is this? So
eventually this is going to create
problems because you can't enslave
people forever.
Maybe you can, but eventually you can't.
Uh yeah. So eventually after certain
battles and wars um the Spartans
defeated Athens then they fought the
people of thieves. Then their army got
significantly decimated in the in the
battle in whatever battle ensued and
because of that the the number of
Spartans dropped drastically and
eventually that led to their downfall
and eventually it was subsumed by the
Roman Empire. So the the major problem
was that Sparta was horribly oppressive.
It enslaved
huge numbers of people and and
maltreated maltreated them horribly. So
that eventually led to the welldeserved
downfall of Sparta.
Nirvana Shanks once again says most
European nations first became prosperous
not through democracy but through
colonial plunder, resource extraction,
imperial exploitation
and later and only later democratized
after wealth had already been
accumulated.
By contrast, India has been democratic
since 1947, yet has struggled to achieve
comparable prosperity, while Singapore
and China have grown rich under
authoritarian systems. What does this
teach you? Given this pattern, is the US
the only major power in history that
truly became prosperous within a
democratic framework? And if so, what
made that possible there and no almost
nowhere else?
Look, the only question you have to ask
yourself with with this in the context
of this question is
is the US truly a democratic nation.
After the uh American Revolution which
we discussed today and the war of
independence which the Americans won,
what happened? We are taught that the
Americans adopted a constitution
and the constitution was ratified
democratically
and then America became a democracy and
it is a great example of the success
that the system of democracy brings to a
nation.
So we have to ask ourselves
was the US at that time truly
democratic? Is it truly democratic
today?
When they won the war of independence
and they drafted this constitution, they
put it to a vote
and that's the democratic process. Now,
who was allowed to vote? Were women
allowed to vote? No. No. No. No. No. No.
No women No women could vote. Were the
true people of America, the natives
allowed to vote? No.
the Okay, let's take a look at the
American Declaration of Independence.
Let's read the text, shall we? Full
text. Let's Let's go to Google. Uh
American
Declaration of Independence full
text. Let's find the full text. This
will be fun. This will be great fun.
This we go to the uh US government's
website.
Don't show again. Thank you.
Uh, I just want to search for one word.
Okay. S A V A G E.
The Declaration of Independence. How
does it refer to these people?
The merciless Indian savages
whose known rule of warfare is an
undistinguished destruction of all ages,
sexes, and conditions. the merciless
Indian savages.
So a nation whose declaration of
independence calls the true natives of
the land merciless savages when it is
these people who writing who wrote the
declaration who were merciless savages.
Right? So the women were not allowed to
vote. The merciless Indian savages were
not allowed to vote. The blacks were
slaves anyway. They were not allowed to
vote. And that's how the constitution
was artified. Do you call this
democracy?
Do you call this democracy? Women could
not vote until the 20th century. You
call that democracy? Yeah.
And today you have a system where you
have only two political parties. Only
two.
Where's the political party for black
people? Where's the political party that
takes care of the interests of the of
the Hispanic people? Where's the
political party for that takes care of
the interests of the native people?
In India, we have political parties for
everything. That's why we are a true
democracy. In the US, you just have two
political parties. Both of which have
the same foreign policy, the same uh you
know, apart from small matters in
domestic policy, everything else is the
same. The US is an autocracy
masquerading as a democracy and that's
why it became so powerful and
prosperous. There's a lesson in all of
this. Democracy doesn't work. If you
want to be powerful, if you want to be
prosperous, you have to be an autocracy.
That's the lesson that you have to
learn.
The Baron Zemo says, "I recently came
across the name library of Ashur
Banipal. Could you please explain what
it was and why it is considered to be so
important in ancient history. Let's go
to the map
and we are going to go to Iraq, present
day Iraq, which well hardly exists
anymore. So we go to Iraq which is we go
to India. We go westwards through a
temporary nation. Then in Persia and
west of Persia we have Mesopotamia which
is the region between the two rivers the
Tigris and the Euphrates. And over here
we will go to Mosul. Mosul is up here in
the north. And near Mosul we going to
search for Nineve
Nine which will be Zum.
Okay. Nineve ruins
ruins and that's where we go. So here we
have the ruins of nin
uh where's the shamash gate saturate
palace and so on. So let's go to the
palace and let us could you please not
do this? Yeah go away please. Thank you.
We go to satellite image. You're going
to see hardly any vegetation at all and
we go in here.
So this is the ruins of Nineve and
that's where somewhere in this area you
had the library of Ashur Banipal. So
Ashur Banipal was the last great king
of the Neo
Assyrian Acadian Empire. Acadian I
believe right
and he was a great scholar. He was a
great uh student
of uh literature. He wanted to know
every religious text that could bring
him good fortune and whatn not and uh he
was a great conqueror also. So wherever
he conquered he would amass the
literature and and added to his library
and uh the library was very well
cataloged very well organized and it was
all in the in the form of clay tablets
mostly written in the cutuniform
language. They may also have have had uh
tablets written in beeswax but those
obviously won't survive because it's an
organic material. So uh
more than 30,000 clay tablets have been
discovered. So what happened to this
library? So Ashra Manipal was this great
conqueror and great great um student of
literature, great uh collector of texts
and uh he used to request his neighbors
and through diplomacy to send him texts
and all that and whichever countries or
or kingdoms he would he would conquer he
would gather gather the texts and add
them to the library. So eventually it
become a very massive library and a very
well organized library probably one of
the first libraries that we know of that
of of which something survives right and
eventually uh
eventually
after his death um the city of Nineve
was was conquered by a combination of
skithians and the the mess who were
portions and and the city was burned
and the library was burned.
And because the library was library was
burned, these clay tablets got baked and
that's why they survived until today.
And the British discovered that. And
today most of these clay tablets are
found in the British library which is
an active crime scene full of stolen
heritage. So uh because of
this gigantic library more than 30,000
texts in various forms some are not well
preserved some are fragmented some are
reasonably well preserved because of
that scholars were able to decipher the
uniform script
and uh you know this library obviously
gives you a lot of information about the
the Mesopotamian
culture,
civilization,
empires and so on. So that's why it's so
important, right?
Okay. Uh
Prem says, "How did the Portuguese
occupy present day Brazil despite the
treaty of Toresas?"
Great question. Treaty of Toresas.
It happened sometimes in the 16th
century. Columbus discovers the
Americas. He thought he was he had
discovered India. He discovered America.
Eventually the Spaniards reached uh the
Americas and they devastated in Octitlan
which is the Azik Empire which is today
Mexico. They also destroyed the Inca
Empire and the Spain Spanish were after
gold. The Portuguese also had tremendous
seafaring capabilities. So the Spanish
and the Portuguese decided that we
should not fight over these things. So
we should divide up the world in two
halves.
Spain should take one half, Portugal
should take the other half. Right? So
they got together, they put the map in
front of them and they divided the world
up and they signed a treaty called which
is called the treaty of Toris
which divided the world into two halves.
So the western half the western
hemisphere so to say was given to the
Spanish. The Spanish would would have
full rights to do whatever they wanted
there. Whichever land they could find
where he did not have Christians, they
could go and conquer the land. They
could genocide the natives. They could
uh enslave the natives. They could rape
the natives. They could do whatever they
want unless they converted to
Christianity in which case they would be
spared too much horror. A little bit of
horror is fine.
So the Spanish they they took the
western hemisphere the Portuguese they
took the eastern hemisphere that's why
the Portuguese vasco ga etc they came to
India that's why India was colonized by
the Portuguese to some extent otherwise
it would if if the Portuguese had taken
the western hemisphere then the
Spaniards would have tried to colonize
India
that's why you have Portuguese uh Goa
there still there are plenty of Goans
who still love Portuguese
Yeah, despite all the operation, that's
a different story. So, yeah, that's the
deal.
Now, the question you're asking is if
you have this division, if Spain is
given the western hemisphere in and
Portugal takes the eastern hemisphere,
how did the Portuguese take over Brazil?
Which is a great question. Let us first
of all go to Google and let's Google
let's find the the the the boundary the
demarcation of the treaty of toatias and
in that is lies the answer okay
all right
what am I doing treaty of to the
so there there's a bunch of islands
called the cabo verde islands cape Verde
Islands and that's and and the treaty
the demarcation line is about like 2,000
km west of the Cape Verde Islands
Cabo Islands. So uh demarcation lines
etc. So if you see
three of the uh let's let's open this
other other one. Okay, give me a second.
It's a Reddit page. Okay, we'll do we'll
do. So as you can see this is the deal.
This is the demarcation. Espña means
Spain and Portugal means Portugal
obviously.
So
about 2,000 kilometers west of the Cape
word islands this this line was drawn.
Okay. And because of that some part of
South America becomes part of territory
that's that that is allocated to
Portugal.
And that's why Portugal went ahead and
took that and they were able they were
allowed to by by the treaty to set forth
u you know to to to set up colonies in
what eventually became Brazil
and eventually over the years they kind
of pushed the envelope and the
boundaries of the treaty of theas and
they set up this big big big colony
called Brazil. So that's how it
happened. It was all part of the treaty.
They did not violate the treaty, but
eventually they did. Eventually, right?
That's the deal.
Okay.
Schub says, "Was Julius Caesar cruel?"
Was Julius Caesar cruel? H
What about
was was Emperor Ashoke cruel?
Let's talk about business. Was Steve
Jobs cruel?
Is Elon Musk cruel? See, Steve Jobs
has a pretty nasty reputation.
He treated his employees pretty harshly.
He made them work very very hard,
very hard hours
and did not give them exceptionally
great pay.
If you look at Elon Elon Musk,
you know, he he orders these surges
like let's get something done which will
take 3 months. Let's do it over a
weekend and all all all hands on board.
No one sleeps. No one no one takes one
minute's rest.
And and and Elon Musk is known to fire
people like that. Hire and fire. When
Elon Musk took over Twitter,
within a few days he fired 85% of the
staff.
Is that cruel?
And the people he retained, he he he
essentially drove them like slaves, you
could say. Obviously, they are paid
money and all. They're not slaves, but
it's it's a metaphor, right? Elon Musk
is not known for empathy.
So, is he a cruel person? Was Steve Jobs
a cruel person?
Isn't Elon Musk trying to achieve
something massive which according to him
will be tremendously beneficial for
humanity?
And unless you push people that that
will take years and years and years and
he wants to achieve this within his
lifetime reaching Mars
and and and if he if he if someday
whenever he dies you don't have that
that that passion and and that push
anymore then that may never happen. So
that's why isn't it justified to push
people that hard that that and and be so
cruel?
Most people can't take it. They have to
leave the company because it's it's the
the pressure is too high. It's very
cruel. Is that cruelty?
Steve Jo is very similar. Was he a cruel
person? Julius Caesar killed so many
people. He essentially conducted
genocide. Was he cruel? Ashoke you could
say did the same thing. Was he cruel?
Samudra Gupta conquered the entire
subcontinent.
Beyond that also he obviously conducted
a lot of warfare. Many people died. many
soldiers of the of the of his opponents
died. Was that cruelty?
Was it? That's the question we to ask
ourselves. You know, Carl Vanuan
Clovitz,
one of the greatest military historians
and writers, strategists,
he wrote,
and I'm paraphrasing here,
that mercy
has no role to play in in warfare. Mercy
is dangerous in warfare. Let's say you
are a general of an army
and you are facing your opponent and you
decide and and and you want to you have
see as you know in a war in a battle in
a war in a military campaign you have
objectives clear objectives I have to go
and capture so and so territory right
that's your objective
now let's say the enemy is surrendering
to you
so then what do you
You have the task of capturing so and so
territory in so and so time. Now the
enemy wants to surrender to you and you
want to be merciful. You want to take
them as prisoners. If you take them as
prisoners, you have to allocate half of
your army to guard them, to feed them
and maybe they want to sabotage you
while pretending to surrender. So should
you surrender and waste your time and
delay your operations which could create
a whole ripple effect and and and defeat
your entire force not just your campaign
but your other generals and your other
armies as well. Should you delay that in
the name of mercy or should you take no
prisoners which means you will kill kill
your kill kill them all. What should you
do?
And in case so that's one example where
being merciful could end up causing much
much more cruelty to your to yourself
and to your people.
And let's say you're fighting a war and
uh the enemy is losing and you don't
want to
you know
destroy the the entire force. So you you
slow down and you don't bombard them
because they they are now almost
decimated. But will that not bog you
down and and give the enemy the chance
to to come and uh potentially defeat you
again? My the whole point is what Carl
won close said is that in warfare there
is there is no place for human
sentiments. It is all mathematical. You
have to keep your sentiments your
emotions out of it. If you try to be
merciful, you actually end up creating
more trouble and and and
you end up being more cruel.
Yeah.
So in in in in these matters, whether it
is the military domain or the business
domain, emotions, sentiments,
there's no place for that.
You you just have to achieve your
objectives as efficiently, effectively,
and rapidly as possible. That
is the most merciful thing to do
essentially.
That's how the world works
unfortunately. Yeah.
Okay. I have as always many more
questions.
Uh but I'm going to have to
I've already crossed two hours. Let's
let's let's take some questions from the
live chat now. Maybe for another 10
minutes.
Okay. So,
um,
so in case you have questions, please
ask. Please feel feel free to ask me.
I'll take a few questions right now.
All right.
Let's see.
Oh, I see that we have super chats. Good
god, people are taking super chats.
Okay. My request to all of you is please
don't take any more super chats because
I have to end the live stream. I'm going
to do a long one tomorrow. So I better
not do a too long a very long one today.
Let me take a few questions right now
from the live from the super chat.
Hersshai says should we follow puppet
kings if they are of any use like king
of bhavnagar is mugghar specialist Jim
rat or prince of me is a chef you should
follow real leaders
that's all I can say
h follow true leaders who are genuinely
worthy of following
devil x first of all thank you sir devil
x says who can be considered the
greatest empire in human straight
including both ancient powers like Rome
and the Mongols of the modern worlds
like the US and what makes it stand
above all others in terms of global
influence and legacy. The greatest
empire in human history is the US
empire, the American empire. Look, there
are various ways of looking at empires
and and evaluating their greatness. Some
would say look at the culture and
civilization. If you have a very good
culture, very high civilization, they
are better and so on. The
straightforward way of looking at empire
is how much have they conquered. Okay,
you may consider it to be a very
barbaric way of looking at looking at
things, but that's the way history
generally
uh judges empires. How do we judge who
wins a war?
We judge who wins a war based on who
takes how much territory. It's as simple
as that. That's why Operation Synindhur
was what? Who won? Can we claim we won?
Did we take any territory?
What was the objective?
Yeah. So,
so which is the greatest empire in human
history? It's the American Empire which
is the US superpower which exists right
now. That is the greatest empire in
world history because they control the
largest uh territory you can think of
and not direct control but indirect
control so that they can hide their
instruments of power.
So, it isn't Rome, it's not the Mongols,
it's the United States. What makes it
stand out? What makes it stand out is
that it has more than 700 extr
territorial uh military bases. It
controls it. It can project power all
across the world. It can intervene
militarily essentially any any part
anywhere in the world at about 60
minutes notice and u it has the the
power to annihilate the whole world.
Legacy I don't know about legacy. Uh so
if you look at old empires as in in the
past I would say the Mongol Empire uh
and obviously the British Empire as well
which still continues in the form of the
US empire. So that's the deal. Um Arvind
says have you played or heard of the NES
Famicon game called Contra?
If there's a real alien invasion could
Earth realistically fight back with
guerrilla tactics.
I haven't played this game. I haven't
heard of it. And we're talking history
today. So, let's deal with history,
please.
Okay. 6P70
Delta says, "Sir Alex 3 is said to be
Putin's favorite star. How good are how
good a leader was he? What was the
condition of Russia? Would the
revolution have taken place if he was in
power?" I haven't studied his history in
great detail, so I can't say. Sorry.
Jasp says civilization is not static.
Human culture values language. Tech is
evolving every day. What good
is historic revisionism?
How can humanity come together to
preserve the species? What's the
question? You're the man. Okay. Thank
you.
Yeah. Everything is evolving every day.
Um that's the nature of the world. What
good is historic revisionism?
uh I have no idea what good is
historical revisionism. What is
important is that we know the true
history so that we can learn the lessons
of history. If we are taught fake
history then we will learn the wrong
lessons and we will be misled. That's
why it's important to set the record of
history straight. Wherever there are
distortions, wherever there is
falsification that needs to be
rectified.
Um how can humanity come forward to to
preserve the species?
By become by becoming multilanetary
because this you know the the cliche
answer is that we should stop war we
should become peaceful blah blah blah
but the fact is that we are a violent
species that will never change. So how
can we preserve the species by becoming
a multilanetary species? Now the
question is who's going to take us
there? Who's going to lead us there?
Right now, it's the United States and
Elon Musk. Is India taking leadership?
Zero.
India is not doing that. So,
India is not going to preserve the
species the way it's going right now.
Project Smiling Buddha says, "Causes of
the Great Depression. Can it happen
again?" The Great Depression, 1930s, the
causes. What were the causes? Financial
market manipulation, etc.
What were the causes of the great
depression?
Yeah, I haven't studied that in detail.
Uh, Indian nomad says not much is known
about the rashtrakutas. I haven't
studied the rashtrautas, sir. I haven't
I'm not a specialist in the rashkutas.
Uh, Harshai says, "How come Maywar
dynasty if every kings fought with the
Turks? We can ignore the bad exceptions
but other dynasties have only two or
three
I don't know
look everybody fought the Turks okay
whoever had to fight them fought them
let's not single out this or that
everyone fought the Turks all the Rajput
fought the Turks
and the Maratas defeated the Turks so
it's this Phoenix says feudalism
becoming dominant in the west due to
merger of core poor in government
but technological development stalled
due to elites becoming mediocre. Bhat
has hope as next generation
are interested in in development and
avoiding traps. Please look at Kukar
Namar 6. Okay. I'm not sure there's a
question in here. There is observations.
All right, sir. Thank you for your
observations and this uh and what you're
saying here. Kuka namar6.
Okay, I shall look into that. I shall
make a note of that. Thank you.
Duresh says, "Your favorite anecdote
from history excluding India." There's
so many. Look, I get these questions all
the time. My favorite empire, my
favorite book, my favorite movie. I
don't have a single favorite of
anything. There's so many so many
examples of these things. So, I can't
give you a single one.
May who vicram says anything about
Hyderabad Nisam may opphan I have not
read anything about this individual so I
can't say thoughts on Andrew Uber Huber
man this is not history sir how he loots
knowledge yeah yeah yeah he he he
yeah that's that's that's a phenomenon
that's that's a long time thing in the
west it's like uh the Wimhof method of
cultural theft he will steal yoga he
will steal steal pranayam, he will steal
bastrika, he will steal kapalabati, he
will put that all together with the
Himalayan cold weather exposure and he
will say it's the wimhoff method and
Andrew Hubberman does the same thing. So
standard uh tactics James, good to see
you James. India in the 40s was slowly
filling with pious British evangelicals
who wanted to not just rule and
administer India but also to redeem and
improve it. Indeed. Indeed. in India is
still being filled with these fantastic
evangelicals who are no longer merely
British, but they're also American and
from various other countries and who are
carrying forth the the flame that the
British the torches that the British
lit. So I suppose James you must be
greatly pleased with what is currently
happening in various parts of India.
In the past in the 40s you had only a
few pious British evangelicals who were
converting a smattering of evil backward
Hindus to superior Christianity. But
today you will see that this is
happening on an industrial scale in
India. So this shall please you and fill
the cockals of your heart with great
warmth. My dear James.
All right. Uh Prashant Sharma says any
book which talks about cast system
before the British.
Um
what's it called? Casts of mind I think
it's called. Give me a second. Let me
Google this. I have the book somewhere
over here in the shelves. But let's
Google this. Casts of mind.
mind by
by Nicholas Dirks is good book. Yes. I'm
not sure if it's about it's it's not
about the cast system before the
British, but it's about uh how the cast
system is is a misnomer and how the
British imposed the four the four uh you
know that that four-pronged cast system
on on India.
Uh 6P70 Delta says, "Excited for
tomorrow's live stream would be awesome.
I look forward to it. I'm also excited
for it. So that brings me to the end of
today's live stream. I am excited for
tomorrow's live stream. It will be an
extended live stream. I am not sure it's
going to be an 8 hour live stream. Most
likely not, but I will
extend it. It'll at least be a 4-hour
live stream. So let's end this today.
Right now at this point in time,
tomorrow 6:00 p.m. India time we will
have the 300th episode of the Ask a
Budget show. Uh I will take all kinds of
questions. It's going to be mainly a
super chat thing but let's see how it
goes. Uh so I look forward to seeing you
all tomorrow 300th episode. Quite an
achievement. I'll see you there
tomorrow. So thank you everybody for the
for the questions. Thank you to everyone
who was here on YouTube, on Twitter, on
on Twitch, on Facebook, wherever else.
Thank you and keep learning, keep asking
questions, keep raising your standards.
I shall see you tomorrow. Thank you very
much. Take care.